Chapter nine. The sermon.
Father Mappel rose and in a mild voice of unassuming authority ordered the
scattered people to condense. Starboard gang way there. Sideway to Larbird.
Larbird gang way to starboard. Midship midship.
There was a low rumbling of heavy sea boots among the benches and a still
slighter shuffling of women's shoes, and all was quiet again, and every eye on
the preacher. He paused a little, then, kneeling in the pulpit's boughs, folded
his large brown hands across his chest, uplifted his closed eyes, and offered a
prayer so deeply devout that he seemed kneeling and praying at the bottom of
the sea. This ended in prolonged solemn tones like the continual tolling of a
bell in a ship that is foundering at sea in a fog. In such tones he commenced
reading the following hymn, but changing his manner towards the concluding
stanzas burst forth with appealing exaltation and joy.
The ribs and terrors of the whale arched over me in dismal gloom, while all God's
sunlit waves rolled by and lift me deepening down to doom. I saw the
opening m of hell with endless pains and sorrows there, which none but they that
feel can tell. Oh, I was plunging to despair. In black distress I called my
God, when I could scarce believe him mine, he bowed his ear to my complaints.
No more the whale did me confine. With speed he flew to my relief, as on a
radiant dolphin born, awful yet bright as lightning shone the face of my
deliverer God. My song forever shall record that terrible, that joyful hour.
I give the glory to my God, his all the mercy and the power.
Nearly all joined in singing this hymn, which swelled high above the howling of
the storm. A brief pause ensued. The preacher slowly turned over the leaves
of the Bible, and at last, folding his hand down on the proper page, said,
"Beloved shipmates, clinch the last verse of the first chapter of Jonah."
And God had prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah.
Shipmates, this book containing only four chapters, four yarns, is one of the
smallest strands in the mighty cable of the scriptures. Yet what depths of the
soul does Jonah's deep sealine sound?
What a pregnant lesson to us is this prophet. What a noble thing is that
canacle in the fish's belly. How billow-like and boisterously grand. We
feel the flood surging over us. We sound with him to the kelpy bottom of the
waters. seaweed and all the slime of the sea is about us. But what is the lesson
that this book of Jonah teaches?
Shipmates, it is a two stranded lesson.
A lesson to us all as sinful men and a
lesson to me as a pilot of the living
God. As sinful men, it is a lesson to us
all because it is the story of the sin, hard-heartedness, suddenly awakened
fears, the swift punishment, repentance, prayers, and finally the deliverance and
joy of Jonah. As with all sinners among men, the sin of this son of Amiti was in
his willful disobedience to the command of God. Never mind now what that command
was or how conveyed, which he found a hard command. But all things that God
would have us do are hard for us to do.
Remember that. And hence he oftener commands us than endeavors to persuade.
And if we obey God, we must disobey ourselves. And it is in this disobeying
ourselves wherein the hardness of obeying God consists.
With this sin of disobedience in him, Jonah still further flouts at God by
seeking to flee from him. He thinks that a ship made by men will carry him into
countries where God does not reign, but only the captains of this earth. He
skulks about the warves of Jopa and seeks a ship that's bound for Tarsish.
There lurks perhaps a hitherto unheeded meaning here. By all accounts, Tarsish
could have been no other city than the modern Kadis. That's the opinion of
learned men. And where is Kadis shipmates? Kadis is in Spain, as far by
water from Jopa as Jonah could possibly have sailed in those ancient days when
the Atlantic was an almost unknown sea.
Because Jopa, the modern Jaffa shipmates, is on the most easterly coast
of the Mediterranean, the Syrian, and Tarsish or Kadis, more than 2,000 mi to
the westward from that, just outside the Straits of Gibralar. See you not then,
shipmates, that Jonah sought to flee worldwide from God. miserable man, oh
most contemptable and worthy of all scorn, with slouched hat and guilty
eyes, skullking from his god, prowling among the shipping like a vile burglar
hastening to cross the seas. So disordered, self- condemning in his
look, that had there been policemen in those days, Jonah, on the mere suspicion
of something wrong, had been arrested, air, he touched a dick. How plainly he's
a fugitive. No baggage, not a hatbox, valise, or carpet bag. No friends
accompany him to the warf with their adus. At last, after much dodging
search, he finds the Tari ship receiving the last items of her cargo. And as he
steps on board to see its captain in the cabin, all the sailors for the moment,
desist from hoisting in the goods to mark the stranger's evil eye. Jonah sees
this, but in vain he tries to look all ease and confidence. In vain essays his
wretched smile, strong intuitions of the men assure the mariners he can be no
innocent. In their gamesome but still serious way, one whispers to the other,
"Jack, he's robbed a widow." Or, "Joe, do you mark him? He's a biggamist. Or
Harry lad, I guess he's the adulterer that broke jail in old Gomorrah. or be
like one of the missing murderers from Sodom. Another runs to read the bill
that stuck against the spile upon the warf to which the ship is mored,
offering 500 gold coins for the apprehension of a paraside and
containing a description of his person.
He reads and looks from Jonah to the bill, while all his sympathetic
shipmates now crowd round Jonah, prepared to lay their hands upon him.
frightened Jonah trembles and summoning all his boldness to his face only looks
so much the more a coward. He will not confess himself suspected, but that
itself is strong suspicion. So he makes the best of it, and when the sailors
find him not to be the man that is advertised, they let him pass, and he
descends into the cabin. "Who's there?"
cries the captain at his busy desk, hurriedly making out his papers for the
customs. "Who's there? Oh, how that harmless question mangles Jonah for the
instant he almost turns to flee again, but he rallies. I seek a passage in this
ship to Tarsish. How soon sail ye, sir?
Thus far the busy captain had not looked up to Jonah, though the man now stands
before him, but no sooner does he hear that hollow voice than he darts a
scrutinizing glance. We sail with the next coming tide. At last, he slowly
answered, still intently eyeing him. No sooner, sir. Soon enough, for any honest
man, that goes a passenger. Ha, Jonah, that's another stab. But he swiftly
calls away the captain from the scent.
I'll sail with you, he says. The passage money. How much is that? I'll pay now.
For it is particularly written, shipmates, as if it were a thing not to
be overlooked in this history that he paid the fair thereof the craft did
sail. And taken with the context, this is full of meaning.
Now Jonah's captain shipmates was one whose discernment detects crime in any,
but whose cupidity exposes it only in the penniless. In this world, shipmates,
sin that pays its way can travel freely and without a passport. Whereas virtue,
if a popper, is stopped at all frontiers. So Jonah's captain prepares
to test the length of Jonah's purse, air he judge him openly. He charges him
thrice the usual sum, and it's asented to. Then the captain knows that Jonah is
a fugitive, but at the same time resolves to help a flight that paves its
rear with gold. Yet when Jonah fairly takes out his purse, prudent suspicion
still molests the captain. He rings every coin to find a counterfeit. Not a
forger, anyway, he mutters, and Jonah is put down for his passage. Point out my
stateateroom, sir, says Jonah. Now I'm travely. I need sleep. Thou looks like
it, says the captain. There's thy room.
Jonah enters and would lock the door, but the lock contains no key. Hearing
him foolishly fumbling there, the captain laughs slowly to himself and
mutters something about the doors of convict cells being never allowed to be
locked within. All dressed and dusty as he is, Jonah throws himself into his
birth and finds the little stateateroom ceiling almost resting on his forehead.
The air is close and Jonah gasps. Then in that contracted hole sunk too beneath
the ship's waterline, Jonah feels the heralding presentiment of that stifling
hour when the whale shall hold him in the smallest of his bowels wards.
screwed at its axis against the side, a swinging lamp slightly oscillates in
Jonah's room, and the ship healing over towards the warf with the weight of the
last bales received, the lamp, flame, and all, though in slight motion still
maintains a permanent oblquity with reference to the room, though in truth
infallibly straight itself, it but made obvious the false lying levels among
which it hung. The lamp alarms and frightens Jonah as lying in his birth
his tormented eyes roll round the place and this thus far successful fugitive
finds no refuge for his restless glance.
But that contradiction in the lamp more and more appalls him. The floor, the
ceiling, and the side are all arai. Oh, so my conscience hangs in me, he groans.
Straight upward so it burns. But the chambers of my soul are all in crookedness.
Like one who after a night of drunken revalry hides to his bed, still reeling
but with conscience yet pricking him as the plungings of the Roman racehorse but
so much more strike his steel tags into him. As one who in that miserable plight
still turns and turns in giddy anguish, praying God for annihilation until the
fit be passed. And at last, amid the whirl of woe he feels, a deep stuper
steals over him. As over the man who bleeds to death, for conscience is the
wound, and there's not to stench it. So, after sore wrestlings in his birth,
Jonah's prodigy of ponderous misery drags him drowning down to sleep. And
now, the time of tide has come. The ship casts off her cables, and from the
deserted wararf, the uncheared ship for Tarsish, all careening, glides to sea.
That ship, my friends, was the first of recorded smugglers. The contraband was
Jonah. But the sea rebels, he will not bear the wicked burden. A dreadful storm
comes on. The ship is like to break. But now when the bosen calls all hands to
lighten her, when boxes, bales, and jars are clattering overboard, when the wind
is shrieking, and the men are yelling, and every plank thunders with trampling
feet right over Jonah's head, in all this raging tumult, Jonah sleeps his
hideous sleep. He sees no black sky and raging sea, feels not the reeling
timbers, and little hears he or heeds he the far rush of the mighty whale, which
even now with open mouth is cleaving the seas after him. I shipmates Jonah was
gone down into the sides of the ship, a birth in the cabin as I have taken it,
and was fast asleep. But the frightened master comes to him and shrieks in his
dead ear, "What meanest thou, oh sleeper? arise. Startled from his
lethargy by that dire cry, Jonah staggers to his feet, and stumbling to
the deck, grasps a shroud to look out upon the sea. But at that moment he is
sprung upon by a panther billow leaping over the bull works. Wave after wave
thus leaps onto the ship, and finding no speedy vent, runs roaring for and aft,
till the mariners come nigh to drowning while yet afloat. And ever as the white
moon shows her a frighted face from the steep gullies in the blackness overhead,
a ghast Jonah sees the rearing bowspread pointing high upward, but soon beat
downward again towards the tormented deep. Terrors upon terrors run shouting
through his soul. In all his cringing attitudes, the god fugitive is now too
plainly known. The sailors mark him more and more certain grow their suspicions
of him, and at last fully to test the truth, by referring the whole matter to
high heaven, they fall to casting lots, to see for whose cause this great
tempest was upon him. The lot is Jonah's, that discovered then how
furiously they mob him with their questions. What is thine occupation?
Whence comest thou? Thy country? What people? But mark now shipmates the
behavior of poor Jonah. The eager mariners but ask him who he is and where
from. Whereas they not only receive an answer to those questions, but likewise
another answer to a question not put by them, but the unsolicited answer is
forced from Jonah by the hard hand of God that is upon him. I am a Hebrew, he
cries. And then I fear the Lord God of heaven who hath made the sea and the dry
land. Fear him, oh Jonah. I well might thou fear the Lord God. Then straight
away he now goes on to make a full confession, whereupon the mariners
became more and more appalled, but still are pitiful. For when Jonah, not yet
supplicating God for mercy, since he but too well knew the darkness of his
deserts, when wretched Jonah cries out to them to take him and cast him forth
into the sea, for he knew that it was for his sake this great tempest was upon
them, they mercifully turn from him, and seek by other means to save the ship.
But all in vain the indignant gale howls louder, and then with one hand raised
invokingly to God, with the other they not unreluctantly lay hold of Jonah. And
now behold Jonah taken up as an anchor and dropped into the sea, when instantly
an oily calmness floats out from the east, and the sea is still as Jonah
carries down the gale with him, leaving smooth water behind. He goes down in a
whirling heart of such a masterless commotion that he scarce heeds the
moment when he drops seething into the yawning jaws awaiting him. And the whale
shoots too all his ivory teeth like so many white bolts upon his prison. Then
Jonah prayed unto the Lord out of the fish's belly. But observe his prayer and
learn a weighty lesson. For sinful as he is, Jonah does not weep and wail for
direct deliverance. He feels that his dreadful punishment is just, he leaves
all his deliverance to God. Contenting himself with this, that spite of all his
pains and pangs, he will still look towards his holy temple. And here,
shipmates, his true and faithful repentance, not clamorous for pardon,
but grateful for punishment. And how pleasing to God was this conduct in
Jonah is shown in the eventual deliverance of him from the sea and the
whale. Shipmates, I do not place Jonah before you to be copied for his sin, but
I do place him before you as a model for repentance. Sin not, but if you do, take
heed to repent of it like Jonah.
While he was speaking these words, the howling of the shrieking, slanting storm
without seemed to add new power to the preacher, who, when describing Jonah's
sea storm, seemed tossed by a storm himself. His deep chest heaved as with a
ground swell. His tossed arms seemed the waring elements at work, and the
thunders that rolled away from off his sworthy brow, and the light leaping from
his eye made all his simple hearers look on him with a quick fear that was
strange to them. There now came a lull in his look as he silently turned over
the leaves of the book once more and at last standing motionless with closed
eyes for the moment seemed communing with God in himself. But again he leaned
towards the people and bowing his head lowly with an aspect of the deepest yet
manliest humility. He spake these words.
Shipmates, God has laid but one hand upon you. both his hands press upon me.
I have read you by what murky light may be mine the lesson that Jonah teaches to
all sinners and therefore to you and still more to me for I am a greater
sinner than you. And now, how gladly would I come down from this mast head
and sit on the hatches there where you sit and listen as you listen, while
someone of you reads me that other and more awful lesson which Jonah teaches to
me as a pilot of the living God. How being anointed pilot, prophet, or
speaker of true things and bidden by the Lord to sound those unwelcome truths in
the ears of a wicked Nineveh, Jonah, appalled at the hostility he should
raise, fled from his mission, and sought to escape his duty and his God by taking
ship at Jopa. But God is everywhere.
Tarsish he never reached. As we have seen, God came upon him in the whale and
swallowed him down to the living gulfs of doom, and with swift slantings tore
him along into the midst of the seas, where the eddying depths sucked him
10,000 fathoms down, and the weeds were wrapped about his head, and all the
watery world of woe bowled over him. Yet even then, beyond the reach of any
plummet, out of the belly of hell, when the whale grounded upon the ocean's
utmost bones, even then God heard the engulfed repenting prophet when he
cried. Then God spake unto the fish, and from the shuddering cold and blackness
of the sea, the whale came breaching up towards the warm and pleasant sun, and
all the delights of air and earth, and vomited out Jonah upon the dry land.
When the word of the Lord came a second time, and Jonah bruised and beaten, his
ears like two seashells still multitudinously murmuring of the ocean.
Jonah did the Almighty's bidding. And what was that, shipmates? To preach the
truth to the face of falsehood. That was it. This, shipmates, is the other
lesson. And woe to that pilot of the living God who slight it. Woe to him
whom this world charms from gospel duty.
Woe to him who seeks to pour oil upon the waters when God has brooded them
into a gale. Woe to him who seeks to please rather than to appall. Woe to him
whose good name is more to him than goodness. Woe to him who in this world
courts not dishonor. Woe to him who would not be true even though to be
false were salvation. Yay! Woe to him who, as the great Pilate Paul has it,
while preaching to others, is himself a castaway.
He dropped and fell away from himself for a moment, then lifting his face to
them again, showed a deep joy in his eyes, as he cried out with a heavenly
enthusiasm, "But oh shipmates, on the starboard hand of every woe there is a
sure delight, and higher the top of that delight, than the bottom of the woe is
deep." Is not the main truck higher than the Kelson is low? Delight is to him a
far, far upward and inward delight, who against the proud gods and commodors of
this earth ever stands forth his own inexurable self. Delight is to him whose
strong arms yet support him when the ship of this base treacherous world has
gone down beneath him. Delight it is to him who gives no quarter in the truth
and kills, burns, and destroys all sin, though he pluck it out from under the
robes of senators and judges. Delight, top, gallant delight is to him who
acknowledges no law or lord but the Lord his God, and is only a patriot to
heaven. Delight is to him whom all the waves of the billows of the seas and the
boisterous mob can never shake from this sure keel of the ages. An eternal
delight and deliciousness will be his.
Who coming to lay him down can say with his final breath, oh father, chiefly
known to me by thy rod, mortal or immortal, here I die. I have striven to
be thine more than to be this world's or mine own. Yet this is nothing. I leave
eternity to thee. For what is man that he should live out the lifetime of his God?
He said no more, but slowly, waving a benediction, covered his face with his
hands, and so remained kneeling till all the people had departed, and he was left
alone in the place.